Civil War Letters and Miscellanea Collection MS 060
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Civil War Letters and Miscellanea Collection
1860-1900
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
MS 060
192
1.75 Linear Feet, 3 boxes
This artificial collection brings together original materials in the WCSU Archives that relates to the Civil War. Materials that are facsimile versions indicate that this repository once possessed an original copy of material. Collection includes: letters, publications and CDVs.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Scope and Contents
The collection is divided in 3 main parts - Regimental Histories/Reunion booklets; Letters and correspondence; and Cartes De Visites. The focus is on Connecticut regiments but there are materials that relate to the 2nd US Sharpshooters and the 1st New York Light Artillery.
Many of the CDVs and letters have accompanying regimental information in the folder.
Correspondence.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Photographs.; Pamphlets; Garlick, Charles D.; United States. Army. Connecticut Infantry Regiment, 16th (1862-1865).; Blakeslee, B.F.; Connecticut. Adjutant-General's Office.; Kent, James S.; United States. Army. Connecticut Infantry Regiment, 8th (1861-1865).; United States. Army. Sharpshooters Regiment, 2nd (1861-1865).; United States. Army. Connecticut Infantry Regiment, 29th (1863-1865).; United States. Army. Connecticut Infantry Regiment, 18th (1863-1865).
- Regimental Histories and Reunion booklets, 41698
  - Sixteenth Regiment, Connecticut Volunteers, 1862-1865. (3 copies), 1889; 41699 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Biographical / Historical
    The regiment was organized in August of 1862 and was active at the battle of Antietam in September of that year. The regiment participated in the following battles: Fredericksburg, VA (Dec 1862), Edenton Road, VA (April 1863), Providence Church Road, VA (May 1863) and Plymouth, NC (Apr 1864).
    Collection is comprised of 3 booklets likely produced to coincide with a regimental reunion in 1889.
    Contains a short regimental history written by Lt. B.F. Blakeslee.
  - A Sketch of the 29th Regiment Connecticut Colored Troops, 1867; 57821 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    General
    Facsimile copy.
  - Hunkey Dorey, ca. 1865 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Letters and correspondence, 57822
  - James Kent (Formerly MS 013), 39249
    Corporal James Kent of Company "G," 2nd United States Sharpshooters. Company "G" was recruited from New Hampshire in December of 1861. Kent was in Augur's Brigade of Rufus King's Division and was assigned to duty in the Defenses of Washington, D. C. until March, 1862. From February until October of 1862, the regiment was involved in the following actions: Great Bethel and Howard's Bridge April 4; Warwick Road April 5; Siege of Yorktown April 5-May 4; Battle of Williamsburg, May 5; Battle of Hanover Court House, May 27; Operations about Hanover Court House April 27-29; Battles of Mechanicsville June 26; Gaines' Mill June 27; Peach Orchard and Savage Station June 29; Turkey Bridge, White Oak Swamp, June 30; Malvern Hill July 1; Duty at Harrison's Landing until August 15; Battles of Groveton August 29; Bull Run August 30; Battle of South Mountain September 14; Battle of Antietam September 16-17. Sharpsburg, Shepherdstown Ford, September 19.
    This collection contains copies and transcripts of seven letters written by Corporal James S. Kent written to his mother and two sisters from February 26, 1862 to September 22, 1862.
    The letters describe the daily routines of Union soldiers during the Civil War. Narratives include description of marches, food, camps, weather, and family information. The letters briefly mention General McDowell, Beauregard, and the death of Willie Lincoln.
    Copies and transcripts of Civil War letters written from the front in Northern Virginia from March to September of 1862.
    Provenance unknown. The original letters went missing from the archives in the early 1990s.
    - Letter from Washington D.C., Feb 1862; 39256 (Box 1, Folder 7, Item 1)
    - Letter from Near Fairfax Seminary, VA, Mar 1862; 39255 (Box 1, Folder 7, Item 2)
    - Letter from Near Bristol, VA, Apr 1862; 39254 (Box 1, Folder 7, Item 3)
    - Letter from Opposite Fredericksburg, VA, May 1862; 39253 (Box 1, Folder 7, Item 4)
    - Letter from Near Falmouth, VA, May 1862; 39252 (Box 1, Folder 7, Item 5)
    - Letter from Near Falmouth, VA, May 1862; 39251 (Box 1, Folder 7, Item 6)
    - Letter from Sharpsburg, MD, Sep 1862; 39250 (Box 1, Folder 7, Item 7)
  - Charles Garlick (formerly MS 007), 38280
    Provenance unknown. The original collection contained 91 letters many of which went missing from the Archives in the early 1980s.
    Charles D. Garlick was a member of the 8th Connecticut Infantry, "I" Company which was organized at Hartford in September of 1861. They were first attached to Parke's Third Brigade in Burnside's Corps.
    Actions the unit participated in included: Burnside's expedition to Hatteras Inlet and Roanoke Island, NC, January 7-February 8, 1862; the Battle of Roanoke Island, NC February 8. The Battle of Newberne, NC March 14; operations against Fort Macon, NC March 23-April 26; Turner's Gap, South Mountain, MD September 14; Battle of Antietam, MD September 16-17; Battle of Fredericksburg, VA, December 12-15; Siege of Suffolk, NC April 12-May 4, 1863; Fort Huger, NC April 19; Edenton Road April 24; Nansemond River May 3; Siege of Suffolk raised May 4; Bermuda Hundred, VA May 5, 1864. Port Walthal Junction, Chester Station, VA May 7; Swift Creek, or Arrow field Church, VA May 9-10; Battle of Drewry's Bluff, VA May 14-16; Battles about Cold Harbor, VA June 1-12; Assaults on Petersburg, VA June 15-18; Battle of Petersburg and Richmond, VA June 16, 1864, to April 2, 1865; New Market Heights, VA September 28-29, 1864; Chaffin's Farm, VA September 29-30, 1864; Battle of Fair Oaks VA, October 27-28, 1864. Occupation of Richmond, VA April 3, 1865. They were mustered out December, 1865.
    Garlick was wounded in action at least twice and provides an articulate description of places and events. He was discharged on September 21, 1864 when his enlistment term expired. (Garlick is listed in some published records under the name Garlie.)
    Sources: unknown, "History - Connecticut Infantry (8th-14th)." Civil War Archive. 16 Dec 2006. 24 Oct 2007 <http://www.civilwararchive.com/Unreghst/unctinf2.htm>. Adjutant-General of Connecticut, Catalogue of Connecticut volunteer organizations, (infantry, cavalry, and artillery,) in the service of the United States, 1861-1865. 1st ed.. Hartford: Brown & Gross, 1869.
    One letter from Charles Garlick is in the collections at the University of North Carolina: http://www.lib.unc.edu/mss/inv/f/Federal_Soldiers_Letters
    - Letter Feb 27, 1862 Roanoke Island, NC, 38293 (Box 2, Item 1)
      General note
      Roanoke Island Feb 27th 1862
      My Dear parents
      I now take my pen in hand to write a few lines to you not from Annapolis but from Roanoke way down in dixy where we landed after 12 days on the water. We left Annapolis on the 13th of Feb and landed the night of the 26th. I will try to give you a few particulars of the voyage. We left Annapolis amid the cheers of the citizens that lined the wharf and a few guns from the two gunboats that lay there at the time and arrived at fortress monroe on the 14th where we lay three days for a storm to pass when we put to sea about 90 miles and found it so rough that we could not enter the inlet and put back to fortress monroe where we stayed another day when we put to sea again and were driven back by a gale about the time that we entered the harbor it began to be foggy and the captain of the boat thought that it was again to clear up so that we could leave in the morning under that impression he thought that as he had got to have more coal he would get it that night and forthwith started for the coal boat when the latter rope caught and we were run ashore under the bowsprit of a schooner which carried away our pilot house? somewhere we did not get any coal that night and had to stay the next two days to repair damages when we put to sea again and it being foggy run past the inlet and the sea being rough we had to put back to of Cape McHenry?? where we lay in quiet until about when a squall struck us and came near sinking us they got up the anchor as soon as possible but not until the seas had swept our hurrycane deck which is about 20 feet from the water at length she was got around before the wind before which she drifted at a fearful rate we the distance of about miles in the space of about six hours we anchored that night in sight of cape Hatteras light then next morning we weighed anchor and made the in a little past noon we went over the swash and anchored for the night in the morning we started for where we were landed on the 26th And here I am in the sand way down in dixyland. We had a very severe storm here last night it rained all night and waked the night and my feet in a puddle of water which vexed me not a little we are ex close to Burnsides head quarters close back of the fort. I should have answered your letters bur I did not get them until last night. I shall have to close this letter you may expect a letter one next time. yours as ever, C. D. Garlick
    - Letter Mar 16, 1862 Roanoke Island, NC, 38292 (Box 2, Item 2)
      Roanoke Island, March 16th, 1862
      I once more seat my self to write you a few lines to let you know how and where I am. I am on the Island yet and am well as I hope these few lines will find you. The expedition has left here for some place which we think is Newburn on the river. I was left here in the Hospital with a hard cold which I caught when I first came on the island the first night it rained like and the water run in to the tent and I waked up and found both my feet nearly covered with water this made me a little out of patience for I had to sit up and sleep the rest of the night I got over my cold before the expedition left here but the troops had gone an board and I had no chance to send word to Capt to send a boat for me and therefore I had to be left. But I shall be sent to the regiment with the rest of the boys that were left. We shall go as soon as they make a landing and get settled which I hope will be soon for it is dull music to stay in the hospital although it is very pleasant here on the island it is like the month of May at home plumb??? trees are in blossom the frogs are peeping the leaves on the trees begin to out. The weather is very warm the birds are singing which makes music to us there is almost every variety of birds here we had a thunder shower here yesterday afternoon it cleared off so that the sun set clear this morning I got up off my secesh bed and went out and it was the most beautiful morning I have seen in a long time. I eat my breakfast of cold rice but johny cakes and butter with a good relish (O by the way we have a woman cook which suits us pretty well) After breakfast one of the boys and my self thought we would take our canteen and walk out and see what we could find we went about a mile and found a (I suppose they call it a house) where we stooped and got our canteen filled with milk at 13 cts per quart The man at the so called house said that he was agoing to plant potatoes next week he said that they generally planted in February but the troops had destroyed the fences so that they were behind. There is one thing that that we have that I guess that you do not yet and that is S H A D at ten cts per price. There is an old slave just here with a basket of eggs to sell.
    - Letter Apr 10, 1862 New Bern, NC, 38291 (Box 2, Item 3)
      Island Apr 10th 1862
      My Dear parents and Brother
      Once more I take my pen in hand to write to you once more I received you letter of the 2nd and last night and was glad to hear from you but was sorry to hear that George was sick with the measles but he is not in the army to have them. I am with the Regt once more we are on Bogues Island. We moved across the sound a few days since to be nearer to our work. I left a few days after I wrote you last I found the encamped about 20 miles from in a small place across the sound from Beaufort We had a very pleasant camp there but we left that for the Island where there is scarce any vegetation except and a few scrubby cedars the Island is very narrow and sandy. I have got to stop for now they have just called me to go on picket guard. I have returned from picket this morning the 7th and now I will try to finish my letter. We had a pleasant time for days after we came across we had quite a time with the rebbles. They send 5 companys from our regiment to drive the rebbels pickets and hold a position near the fork which we did through saturday until sunday morning amidst the explosion of bomb shell from the fort which passed just over our heads and burst within a short distance of us some of the pieces coming pretty near us one piece passed under one mans leg as he was sitting on the ground and struck his gunbarrel with such force as to break it. We were relieved on Sunday morning by another squad which were relieved the next morning and so on while they were building the battery which is nearly completed. It is the 5 11 inch mortars 3 8 inch and 3 long 32 pound rifled siege guns their range is 5 miles and the battery is within a mile of the fort they shoot steel pointed wrought iron balls which we imagine will do some executing if they are well aimed which I think they will be. Probably we shall have some more work in a few days but it will be mostly with the artillery I think about those shirts I shall not them I drew some new ones which were due me day before yesterday. I will let you know if I need them we were payed off a few days ago and last night the Express agent came in camp with envelopes. Lieut. Roberts got some of him and I sent Father in a package to Albin Ferris with and Hilliard change is very scarce her so I did not pay the express you can go to and get it and use it if you want it or do what you think best with it. I want you to use some of it for me When George gets well I want the Daguerreotype of Father and you and George in one case you and Father in one side and George in the other and send it to me by mail or express as you think best the express does not come any farther than Newburn. I think it would come as safe by mail so anyway and I think of going down to the this afternoon and take a bath in the salt water it is but a few steps from camp if I had any way to send them I would send you some of the shells that lay strewn along the beach I have some in my napsack which I shall bring home with me if I come the oysters are plenty here also clams all they cost is the time of digging them. We have another article I have not mentioned and that is Salmon trout at five cents apiece I shall have to close for the drum has beat for dinner. So good by for this time.
      From you affectionate son
      Charles D. Garlick
      P.S. Direct to Charles D. Garlick
      Co I 8th Regt. C. V.
      Third Brigade
      Burnsides division
      Newbirn N. C.
      Give my respects to all
      P. S. Tell Grandpa that we had a foot race with the rebbles the other day I thought when I was at home I could run some but these southern sand pipers beat all the running I ever saw the other day when we were chasing them over the sand hills when we got a sight at them they were bobbing over the sand knoles like so many toads they were far in advance and gaining all the time and hollowing come on you damed yankees I guess they found us coming (I do) You spoke about some secesh I have got a secesh Testament which I will send if I have a chance. Charles Irwin was sent home recruiting perhaps you will have a chance to see him.
    - Letter Sep 28, 1862, Sharpsburg, MD, 38290 (Box 2, Item 4)
      General Hospital near Sharpsburg Sunday Sept 28th 1862 My Dear Parents. I thought that I would have a few more lines written to you to day to let you know how I was getting along. I am feeling some better to day and hope to be about before long, I received a letter from home this morning and was glad to hear from you once more. When I am well enough to stand it the Surgeon will give me a furlough to come home but I will have to pay my own expenses therefore please to send me about twenty dollars in a letter. Send it as soon as you receive this. The reason that I send for this money is that I can not get my descriptive to draw my pay. This pay day the reason I cannot get it is because the company book are all left in Washington. The wounded are all going home on furloughs as fast as they get able. A great many have gone. Please tell Robert Erwin that I received a letter from him to day and was very much pleased to hear from him and should answer it if I was able as soon as I get well I will try to answer all letters that I receive during my indisposition. I close in hopes of soon being where I can tell you how I feel without the use of pencil and paper. Give my respects to all enquiring friends. I remain your affectionate Son Charles D. Garlick P. S. The directions are Charles D. Garlick Co I 8th Regt. C. V. General Hospital near Sharpsburg Washington Co. Md. (Care Dr. Warner) (Surgeon in charge)
    - Letter (2) Sep 28, 1862 Sharpsburg, MD, 38289 (Box 2, Item 5)
      Sharpsburg, Maryland Tuesday Sept 28th 1862 Dear Father I write you this by the hand of my friend Bardsey Gilbert who is taking care of me to let you know where I am and how I am getting along. I was unlucky enough the day of the battle to get a bullet in my body. It went in to my back near my left shoulder and is in my body now but the Surgeon says that it is doing well. The Surgeon says that the bullet will not trouble me much. He thinks it was a terrible battle we had just half of our company in killed and wounded. The killed are David Lake and Robert Ferriss and a man by the name of George Burch. Robert Ferriss was shot through the breast. He fell dead. Lake was shot in the hip and the ball glanced upwards into his bowels. He lived until the next day. The wounded are Robert Stuart, Barth Latin (?), Wm Terrell, Timothy T. Terrell, John Geeley, Orville Sprague, Oscar Squire, John McKay(?), Charles N. Erwin, and myself but there is none of them that is dangerously wounded. We had a color guard the day of the battle of two sergeants and seven corporals and they were all killed or wounded except the loss in our regiment is about 200 killed and wounded. Our Lieut. Col, was wounded very severely in the leg but I believe that he has not had it amputated although they thought it would be necessary. I received a letter from mother the day before we left Washington and should have answered it before this but I have had no opportunity. I hope to be well enough before a great while to write to you myself and then I will give you the full particulars of our march and doings since leaving Washington. Give my respects to all enquiring friends and now farewell for this time. I remain your dutiful son Charles Garlick P.S.When you write to me the directions will be Charles Garlick Co I 8th Regt, C. V. General Hospital Near Sharpsburg Washington Co.?? Care Dr. Warner Md Surgeon in Charge Chas. Garlick
    - Letter July 28, 1863 New Haven, CT, 38288 (Box 2, Item 6)
      U. S. Army General Hospital,
      New Haven, Conn., July 28th 1863
      Dear parents
      I now take my pen in hand to write to you once more. I have written to you twice and have not received an answer yet. I am feeling quite well now and hope that you are the same. We have not been paid yet but expect to get some rocks pretty soon. I am in the office now as the adjutant's orderly. It is a pretty good place. We have a good deal to do here now in making out details for escorting conscripts to camp. There was a number tryed to run away the other night two was shot dead one was pretty badly wounded he was brought up to the hospital his left arm was amputated on Sunday morning. I guess he will not try to get away again. They were substitutes.
      There was several of my regiment came here on the boat the other night but none from my Company but they said the boys were all well and are at Portsmouth V.A. now they have a first rate camp and the duty is light. Give my respects to all that enquire and please write soon. As ever your affectionate son,
    - Letter of Aug 7, 1863 New Haven, CT, 38281 (Box 2, Item 13)
      Knight General Hospital
      New Haven, Conn., August 7th 1864
      Dear parents and Brother
      I now take my pen in hand to write you a few lines. I am well for me and hope these lines will find you the same. I am getting along first rate here in the office but have considerable to do. I had to work till after dark tonight and it is now after ten o'clock that I take my pen in hand to write you these lines. Perhaps it will be the last that I shall write you from here. I am going to the regiment in a few days (We are not paid yet but expect it soon and then we leave for the front. I shall try to home before I go away if I do not you must not worry about me for I think that I have not been two years in the service for nothing. I shall try to keep my self for one short year. I think I can do it and then the army may whistle before they get me again. (I would not wonder)
      I will send enclose in this a picture of Bill Sergeant with no arms.
      Give my respects to all that enquire and please write soon.
      From your affectionate son.
      Chas. D. Garlick
      P.S. Direct to Knight U.S.A. General Hospital
      New Haven
      Conn
    - Letter Aug 13, 1863 New Haven, CT, 38287 (Box 2, Item 7)
      Knight U. S. A. General Hospital
      New Haven August 13th 1863
      I now take my pen in hand to write you a few lines. I am in good spirits now and hope these few lines will find you the (in the crossed out) same. By the time that this reaches you I shall be on my way to the front. We leave here at the time o'clock Boat tomorrow morning for New York. I could not come home before I went but do not worry about me. I shall be home soon to stay some time if nothing happens and I do not think there will.
      I will send my valise by express to you among the lot is a pair of boots for George. Tell him to wear them for me (and a coat also). Also a dress coat for Father. It is too large for George. I will write to you soon as I get to a stoping place. Yours as ever in haste.
      Your affectionate son
      Co I 8th Regt.
      Conn. Vols.
    - Letter Aug 30, 1863, Portsmouth, VA, 38286 (Box 2, Item 8)
      U. S. ARMY GENERAL HOSPITAL,
      New Haven, Conn., 186
      Portsmouth, Va.
      Aug 30th 1863
      I now take this opportunity to write you a few lines. I am very well though somewhat tired after my journey but it is not finished yet. The Regt is about 50 miles from here way down in the middle of the dismal swamp and we are stooping here until we can get transportation down there. When I wrote you last we were at Bedlowes Island and now we are way down in old Virginia.